Guide to the Cormac K. H. O'Malley Papers AIA.019
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Cormac K. H. O'Malley Papers
1930-2014
1969-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
O'Malley, Cormac K. H.
AIA.019
33 Linear Feet in 19 record cartons, 7 manuscript boxes, 7 oversize flat boxes, and 1 photograph box.
Cormac K. H. O'Malley (1942-) is an attorney who has been an international corporate counsel and consultant. Since the 1960s, O'Malley has been active in the New York Irish community, joining various cultural, academic and social organizations. This collection includes materials regarding Irish-American and Irish cultural, educational, charitable, historical and political affairs. Materials include correspondence, newsletters, brochures and promotional material for the American Committee for Ulster Justice, the Irish American Cultural Institute, the Irish American National Bicentennial Committee, The American Ireland Fund, the Irish Georgian Society, and the O'Malley Clan Association. Also included are articles and texts about the Northern Ireland political and military crisis during the 1970s and lobbying material for the 1972 U.S. Congressional Hearings on Northern Ireland. O'Malley collected the materials through his contacts with various organizations in the Irish communities in New York, Boston, and Dublin, and his involvement with the struggle for civil rights in Northern Ireland.
Custodial History
In 1980 Cormac O'Malley deposited 27 cubic feet of material in the archives of St. John's University in Jamaica, New York. It remained unprocessed and unused for the next 20 years. In December 2000, while President of the Board of Advisors for New York University's Glucksman Ireland House, O'Malley transferred the collection to the Archives of Irish America at the Tamiment Library as a permanent donation. Approximately 20 linear feet of materials were initially transferred in December 2005 and an additional 7 linear feet were transferred in March 2001. The accession number associated with this donation is 2000.025. A 2015 accrual (2015.047) from Glucksman Ireland House added 8.5 linear feet that were incorporated into the collection as Subseries IF and an addition to Series III. A 2016 accretion (2016.069) from Glucksman Ireland House added 6 linear feet that were incorporated into the collection as Subseries IG, Subseries IH, Subseries II, Subseries IJ, and an addition to Subseries ID.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Biographical Note
Cormac Kevin Hooker O'Malley was born in Dublin, Ireland in 1942. His father was Ernie O'Malley (1897-1957), Irish revolutionary, author and patron of the arts, and his mother was American artist and socialite Helen Huntington Hooker (1905-1993). Upon the death of his father, O'Malley left Ireland to finish his education in the United States, obtaining a BA from Harvard in 1965 and a JD from Columbia University in 1970. He pursued a career in international law in New York, first with Curtis, Mallet-Prevost, Colt & Mosle, then, from 1981 with Bristol-Myers, living in Mexico, Brussels, London, and New York according to the dictates of his career. In the 1990s, upon retirement from Bristol-Myers Squibb, O'Malley became active as an advisor to Glucksman Ireland House at New York University.
When in New York, O'Malley was involved with the Irish American community, joining various cultural, academic, and social organizations, such as the Friendly Sons of St. Patrick in the City of New York, the American Committee (later Conference) for Irish Studies, and the Irish Arts Center in New York. During the 1970s-1980s, O'Malley served as an officer or on the board of four such groups: the American Irish Historical Society, the Irish American National Bicentennial Committee, the Ireland Fund (now the American Ireland Fund) and the National University of Ireland Club. O'Malley also had an interest in the civil rights struggle in Northern Ireland. From 1971-1978 he served as national coordinator for the American Committee for Ulster Justice, a group of Irish American lawyers and activists intent on eliminating anti-Catholic discrimination and exposing British complicity in the region's conflict.
O'Malley is the author of "The Publication History of On Another Man's Wound" in New Hibernia Review 7:3 (2003): 136-139 and co-author with Keith Highet of Current Aspects of Doing Business in Black Africa(American Bar Association, 1975).
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of material included in this collection reflects O'Malley's involvement in various Irish American cultural, social, academic, and political organizations between 1964 and 2011. Materials include memoranda, transcripts, correspondence, posters, publications, scrapbooks, promotional materials, research notes, newspaper clippings, research files, agenda, and minutes. The collection documents various aspects of Irish American social and cultural life, with materials concerning specific cultural or academic organizations. Also present are materials concerning efforts to lessen conflict in Northern Ireland during the Troubles, with specific emphasis on the American Committee for Ulster Justice. A 2015 accrual has added material related to O'Malley's involvement with Glucksman Ireland House, GRIAN Association, and other Irish-American cultural groups. A 2016 accretion added material documenting O'Malley's involvement in The American Ireland Fund, the Irish Georgian Society, the O'Malley Clan Association, and the Granuaile Trust of the O'Malley Clan.
Arrangement
Organized into four series with sub-series, as follows:
Series I. Cultural, Social, and Academic Organizations, 1964-2011
Subseries IA. General
Subseries IB. American Irish Historical Society (AIHS)
Subseries IC. Irish American Cultural Institute (IACI)
Subseries ID. Irish American National Bicentennial Committee
Subseries IE. National University of Ireland Club
Subseries IF. Glucksman Ireland House
Subseries IG. American Ireland Fund Records
Subseries IH. Irish Georgian Society Records
Subseries II. O'Malley Clan Association Records
Subseries IJ. Granuaile Trust of the O'Malley Clan Records
Series II. American Committee for Ulster Justice (ACUJ), 1968-1981
Subseries IIA. ACUJ Organizational Material
Subseries IIB. U.S. Congressional Hearings on Northern Ireland
Subseries IIC. ACUJ Research Materials for 1972 Congressional Hearings
Series III. Publications and Clippings, 1959-1981
Series IV. Ephemera, 1930-2000
Subseries IA, IB, IC, IE, and IF are arranged alphabetically. Subseries ID, with the exception of the 2016 accretion, is arranged alphabetically; the accretion has not been arranged by an archivist. Subseries IG, IH, II, and IJ have not been arranged by an archivist. Subseries IIA is arranged alphabetically, and Subseries IIB and IIC are arranged chronologically. Series III is arranged chronologically and Series IV is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America Periodicals Collection AIA 004
Archives of Irish America Vertical File Collection AIA 013
Irish Republicanism Collection AIA 022
Separated Material
A small collection of pamphlets and other publications regarding the struggle for recognition of the Irish Republic collected by O'Malley's father Ernie O'Malley (1897-1957) have been removed to the AIA Pamphlet Collection (AIA 047). Promotional material, event programs, brochures and newsletters O'Malley collected from various Irish American organizations have been integrated into the AIA Vertical Files (AIA 013), AIA Periodicals Collection (AIA 004), and the Irish Republicanism Collection (AIA 022).
Promotional materials; Printed material.; Clippings (information artifacts); Scrapbooks.; Correspondence.; Irish Americans -- Social life and customs.; New York (N.Y.); Northern Ireland -- History -- 1969-1994.; Notes.; O'Dwyer, Paul, 1907-1998; Association of Irish Business Graduates; An Taisce (National Trust for Ireland); American-Irish Historical Society; American Irish Foundation; American Irish Development Committee, Inc.; American Committee for Ulster Justice; McKiernan, John Thomas, 1915-2004; MacGowran, Jack, 1918-1973; Connolly, James B. (James Brendan), 1868-1957; Healy, James A.; Irish American Cultural Institute; Canadian Association for Irish Studies; National University of Ireland Club; Irish American National Bicentennial Committee; United States. Congress; Claidheamh Soluis (New York, N.Y.); United States Chamber of Commerce in Ireland; Irish Georgian Society; O'Malley Clan Association; American Ireland Fund
- Series I. Cultural, Social and Academic Organizations, 1964-2014; 104052
  - Subseries IA. General, 318800
    Scope and Content Note
    This subseries consists of correspondence, promotional materials, bulletins, and notes about several Irish and Irish American cultural, charitable, education, and academic organizations of which O'Malley was an officer or member, including the American Irish Foundation, An Taisce (National Trust of Ireland), and the Canadian Association for Irish Studies. Of particular note are folders concerning the New York Shakespeare Festival's 1973 memorial to Jack MacGrowan and the 1975 donation of the James A. Healy Collection to the Sligo Museum and Library.
    - American Irish Development Committee, Inc. New York, 1968-1969; 104115 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Irish Foundation: National, 1964-1977; 104114 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - An Claidheamh Soluis: The Irish Arts Center (The Irish Rebel Theatre), 1972-1974; 104113 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - An Taisce (National Trust for Ireland): General, 1970-1977; 104112 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - An Taisce: Publications, 1970-1977; 262442 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Association of Irish Business Graduates, 1972; 104111 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Canadian Association for Irish Studies, 1970-1980; 104110 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Invitations to Events of Various Irish and Irish American Organizations, 1975-1981; 104106 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Irish Association for American Studies, 1974; 104109 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Irish Associations: General, 1975-1981; 104105 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Irish Economy: Organizations, Events and Notes, 1969-1981; 104108 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Jack MacGowran Memorial: New York Shakespeare Festival, 1973; 104107 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Sligo Museum and Library (James A. Healy Collection Donation) (See also Box 22), 1975; 104104 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - United States Chamber of Commerce in Ireland: Events and Newsletters, 1977-1981; 104103 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Subseries IB: American Irish Historical Society (AIHS), 104092
    This subseries consists of materials related to the activities of the American Irish Historical Society during the period in which O'Malley was directly involved in the organization (1968-1981). Materials relate to the society's library and art collection. The subseries also includes an index to the Journal of the American Irish Historical Society drafted by O'Malley in 1974.
    - Annual Dinner Materials, 1968-1973; 104102 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Annual Dinner Materials, 1973; 262467 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Annual Dinner Materials, 1974-1981; 104101 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Art Committee: Library Matters, 1972-1973; 104100 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Art Committee: Library Matters, 1974; 104099 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Bulletin, 1973; 104097 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Event Programs, Announcements, 1972-1981; 104096 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Financial Statement, Dec 31, 1973; 104095 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Drafts for an Index to the Journal of the AIHS, 1974; 104094 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Publications, undated; 104093 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Subseries IC: Irish American Cultural Institute (IACI), 104081
    This subseries consists of materials concerning the Irish American Cultural Institute (founded in St. Paul, Minnesota in 1962) during the period in which O'Malley was directly involved in the organization (1967-1981). Materials relate to the organization's Irish Fortnight Series of lectures in New York which brought over speakers from Ireland to discuss a variety of cultural topics.
    - Annual Awards Dinner (First), 1974-1975; 104091 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1977; 104090 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Irish Fortnight Committee in New York, 1972-1973; 104089 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Irish Fortnight Committee in New York, 1974-1975; 104088 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Irish Fortnight Committee in New York, Jan 1976-Sep 1976; 104087 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Irish Fortnight Committee in New York, Oct 1976-Dec 1976; 104086 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Irish Fortnight Committee in New York, 1977; 104085 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - New Jersey Chapter, 1972-1977; 104084 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Ohio Chapter, 1973-1975; 104083 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Washington, DC Chapter, 1972-1976; 104082 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Subseries ID: Irish American National Bicentennial Committee (IANBC), 104056
    This subseries consists of materials concerning the Irish American National Bicentennial Committee (1973-1978), established to involve Irish Americans in the activities surrounding the 200th anniversary of the founding of the United States. The organization had chapters in several states through which it sponsored events and projects, such as the participation of the Irish tall ship Creidne in Operation Sail. Of note in this subseries is O'Malley's "Planning Guide to the Irish American Bicentennial Celebration in Your Community" (1975) and an index card file of select people in the Irish American community living on the East Coast.
    The 2016 accretion includes correspondence between O'Malley and state chapters of the Committee and other Irish and Irish American organizations, research files on topics related to the work of the Committee, and files documenting the work of the Art Committee and the Research Committee.
    - Contacts (Index Card File), 1974-1975; 104080 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1976; 104079 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1976; 262485 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Budget, Action and Funding Proposals, 1974-1975; 104077 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Bicentennial: National Conference of Catholic Bishops Committee for the Bicentennial, 1974-1976; 104076 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Bicentennial: Clippings of Bicentennial Celebrations in America, 1975-1976; 104075 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Bicentennial: "Planning Guide to an Irish American Bicentennial Celebration in Your Community" by Cormac O'Malley, Jun 7, 1975; 104074 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Events and Projects: Comhaltas Ceoltoiri Eireann Concert, 1975; 104071 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Events and Projects: Directory of Irish Americans, 1974; 104073 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Events and Projects: Historical Exhibition on the Irish in America, 1974-1975; 104072 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Events and Projects: Irish American Studies Conference, 1975; 104070 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Events and Projects: Operation Sail 1976, Irish Ship Creidne participates in U.S. Project, 1975-1976; 104069 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Events and Projects: Speech at Philadelphia Friendly Sons of St. Patrick, by Cormac O'Malley, Mar 16, 1976; 104067 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Events and Projects: Theatre Projects, 1975; 104068 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Memoranda, Jan-May 1975; 262486 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Promotional Material, 104066 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Reference Materials: Funding Programs, undated; 104063 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Promotional Material: Guide to Irish American Aspects of New York, 1975; 104065 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Research Materials, 1973-1976; 104078 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - State Chapters: NY Agenda, Proposals for Action and Funding, Newsletter, 1974-1976; 104061 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - State Chapters: NY Correspondence, Promotional Material, 1974-1976; 104060 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - State Chapters: CA, CT, DE, MA, MI, 1974-1976; 104059 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - State Chapters: OH, PA, RI, TX, 1974-1976; 104058 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Dissolution, 1977-1978; 104057 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 2016 accretion, 1973-1976 (Box 28, Box 29, Folder 1-5)
  - Subseries IE. National University of Ireland Club, 104053
    This subseries consists of materials concerning O'Malley's membership in the New York branch of the National University of Ireland Club during the period of 1968-1981.
    - National University of Ireland Club (New York) (I), 1968-1975; 104055 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - National University of Ireland Club (New York) (II), 1968-1975; 262496 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - National University of Ireland Club (New York) (III), 1976-1981; 104054 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Subseries IF: Glucksman Ireland House Records, 1997-2008; 591133
    This subseries contains materials documenting O'Malley's involvement in NYU's Glucksman Ireland House (GIH) during the years 1999-2014. Materials include correspondence with GIH donors, Irish Studies course syllabi and curriculum planning documentation, promotional material such as brochures and postcards, correspondence and memoranda concerning film and lecture events, correspondence concerning potential archival collections for the Archives of Irish America, and materials concerning the activities of the GIH Advisory Board, including correspondence, memoranda, and meeting minutes.
    - Glucksman Ireland House Records, 1997-2008 (Box 21, Box 24, Box 25, Box 26, Box 27)
  - Subseries IG: American Ireland Fund Records, 1965-2014
    Scope and Contents
    This subseries documents O'Malley's involvement in the American Ireland Fund from its incorporation in 1976 to 2014 and his membership in one of its predecessors, the American Irish Foundation from 1965 to 1977. The bulk of the records document O'Malley's service as secretary from 1976 to 1981 and as a member of the Advisory Committee from 1984 to 1988. Materials include correspondence; board agenda and minutes; the American Ireland Fund's publication, Connections, later titles Connect; bylaws, financial reports, newspaper clippings, and ephemera.
    Historical Note
    The American Ireland Fund was created in 1987 when The Ireland Fund and the American Irish Foundation merged. It supports projects in Ireland and the United States focused on peace and reconciliation, arts and culture, education, and community development.
    - American Ireland Fund Records, 1965-2014 (Box 29, Folder 6-22, Box 30, Folder 1-10, Box 34, Folder 1-8)
  - Subseries IH: Irish Georgian Society Records, 1977-2011
    This subseries documents O'Malley's involvement in the Irish Georgian Society from 1977 to 2011. The bulk of the records documents his service as a member of the Board of Directors from 1977 to 2005 and include correspondence with other directors, including Desmond Guinness, the founder of the Society; financial material; reports on funding and buildings nominated for conservation; newsletters; and board agenda and minutes.
    The Irish Georgian Society promotes awareness and the protection of Ireland's architectural heritage and decorative arts. It was established in 1958.
    - Irish Georgian Society Records, 1977-2011 (Box 30, Folder 11-18, Box 31, Box 32, Folder 1-8)
  - Subseries II: O'Malley Clan Association Records, 1959-2011
    This series documents O'Malley's participation in the O'Malley Clan Association between 1959 and 2011, including his tenure as Tanaiste of the Clan in 1993 and as Chieftain in 1994. The records include correspondence, research files, ephemera, and financial documents. The bulk of the records document the planning of the annual O'Malley Clan Rallies in County Mayo, Ireland. Other records include family trees and newspaper clippings on members of the Association in the research files and correspondence with other members of the Association regarding clan history, Rallies, and membership issues.
    The Granuaile Trust was established in Ireland in 1986 to create scholarships, research, and grants for members of the O'Malley Clan and others. The Trust closed in 2000.
    - O'Malley Clan Association Records, 1959-2011 (Box 32, Folder 9-49, Box 33, Folder 1-20)
  - Subseries IJ. Granuaile Trust Records, 1986-2000
    This subseries documents O'Malley's participation in the Granuaile Trust of the O'Malley Clan in Ireland and The Granuaile Trust Foundation in the United States between 1986 and 2000. The material for the Granuaile Trust of the O'Malley Clan documents his work as a member of the board of trustees from 1986 to 2000 and the material for the The Granuaile Trust Foundation documents his work to establish the Foundation and make it a successful organization.
    The Granuaile Trust Foundation was established in 1988 to supplement the efforts of and to raise funds for support of the the Granuaile Trust. It closed in 2000.
    - Granuaile Trust Records, 1986-2000 (Box 33, Folder 21-31)
- Series II. American Committee for Ulster Justice (ACUJ), 1968-1981; 103952
  This series consists of organizational and research materials generated by O'Malley while he served as national coordinator for the American Committee for Ulster Justice (ACUJ) between 1971-1978. Established by Irish American lawyers and activists in response to civil rights violations in Northern Ireland, the ACUJ focused on educating and lobbying American politicians to intercede with the British government. Materials in this series include correspondence, memoranda, publications, research notes, press releases, newspaper clippings, transcripts of Congressional hearings, and position papers released by the British and Irish governments.
  - Subseries IIA. ACUJ Organizational Material, 104032
    This subseries consists of correspondence, memoranda, publications, research notes, and press releases related to the regular activities and the functions of the ACUJ.
    - Correspondence, Aug 1971-Dec 1971; 104051 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Aug 1971-Dec 1971; 263681 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Jan 1972-Feb 1972; 104050 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Mar 1972-May 1972; 104049 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Jun 1972-Dec 1972; 104048 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, undated; 104047 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: Brochure, 1972; 266364 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence for the Ad Hoc Committee for Business and Professional Men Interested in Northern Ireland, Mar 1972-May 1972; 104046 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence for the Ad Hoc Committee for Business and Professional Men Interested in Northern Ireland, Mar 1972-May 1972; 263698 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence for the Committee to Review Various Prospects Regarding the Future Status of Northern Ireland, 1972; 266365 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Memos, Notes (I), 1971; 104043 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Memos, Notes (II), 1971; 262497 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Memos, Notes (III), 1972, undated; 104042 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Memos, Notes (IV), 1973; 104041 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Notes (I), 1972; 104039 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Notes (II), 1972; 262534 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Notes, 1973; 104038 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Notes, 1974; 104037 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Notes, 1975; 104036 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Notes, 1976; 262535 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Newsletters ACUJ (Incomplete), 1972-1977; 104033 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1971-1972; 104034 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Press Releases, Invitations, Lists, Organizational Structure, 1971-1972; 104035 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Subseries IIB. U.S. Congressional Hearings on Northern Ireland, 104007